everything in the food you eat can be
broken up into two general categories
now there's not perfect agreement among
nutritional scientists
what exactly goes in each category but
this is what i've settled on so
basically you've got nutrients and
non-nutrients
right in order for it to be called a
nutrient it has to be used by the
organism to grow survive
reproduce and either use for metabolic
purposes or excreted first structure
things like fingernails hair shells now
of the three major categories of
nutrients you've got macros
minerals and vitamins now let's see this
little carolina blue line going between
the minerals and vitamins that means
everything in that category is typically
given
to you in terms of recommendations of
make sure you eat at least this amount
or you know don't eat less than this the
things that are in the dark blue over
there
are considered a center body cannot
synthesize it itself you so you've got
to consume it through your diet
and things in the brown other than one
exception everything else in this board
is organic so the only inorganic
molecule on here are the actual minerals
and that little purple triangle
indicates that these things have an
effect
within an acute hours or days so for
example if you have a super high
carbohydrate meal or a high fat meal you
will feel that
you know immediately or within like a
couple of days you don't necessarily
feel
differences in minerals and vitamins
acutely it probably takes days weeks or
even months
now on the non-nutrient side we have
three basic categories and the two that
you need to pay most attention to notice
that they're both the baby carolina blue
so we tend to give you recommendations
of
get at least this minimal amount but we
don't tell you you know how to stop at
the top end
it's fiber and phytochemicals now fiber
again has an acute effect if you smash
down 25 grams of fiber you'll
pay that price pretty quickly and it is
not technically considered a nutrient
because it's not a part of
growing reproduction or survival it's
not broken down from metabolism
most of it some of it obviously is and
it's not excreted for structure having
said that
some do consider it a nutrient so i call
it the not a nutrient technically but
incredibly important again try to live
your life without fiber you'll
understand why it's important
also has uh the purple triangle like i
mentioned in terms of phytochemicals
this is a very great area because we've
basically just been learning about these
in the last 10 years so
a lot of folks actually categorize
phytochemicals as nutrients because
they're not a part of growth
reproduction metabolism or excretion
but they're very clearly important for
survival especially post-pubescent so
aging well highly dependent on vital
chemicals over 25 000 of them they're
brilliantly broken into two major
categories but we're going to get into
more of this detail in separate videos
so let's kind of stop there with our
phytochemicals
going back to your macros three major
categories protein fats carbs you know
about these and i've added a little pink
line to differentiate these are the
opposite now so these are the ones we
say don't eat
more than these amounts generally the
orange blocks and indicate that these
are converted to smaller molecules
basically through metabolism and the end
product is co2 and h2o now the only
thing that kind of throws things off
here is water so water is technically
a nutrient it's not technically it's
inorganic so it should be kind of or
the gold color but it's not and we tend
to give you the minimum amount so make
sure you drink at least this amount so
water technically macronutrient but
clearly it carries no calories
there the water is also the only thing
on this board that is absolutely
required for all living things
getting back to your macronutrients
let's start with protein and you can
split this up into three major
categories and again you see
half of these are blue or essential so
those are your nine essential amino
acids then you've got your six
non-essential amino acids then you have
another category here which is the blue
outline and these are
the amino acids that are conditionally
essential so your body can make some of
them but not enough to meet your
requirements
okay in terms of fat you've got a whole
host of fatty acids you can look them up
i've called them the rest here
and then you have two one of them being
an omega-3 acid and another one being an
omega-6 acid that are essential
and then you have two that are again
conditionally essential think dha as a
growing young child or a baby
required as you become adult not
necessarily now you'll also notice wait
a minute what about the carbohydrates
well sorry folks but they're not
technically essential
go back to what i mean by essential
doesn't mean they're not important
so for minerals you can actually break
this down up and the first category is
actually macro so typically when we say
the word macro we almost always assume
we're thinking about protein carbs and
fat but there are macro minerals and we
call them that because
not only are they essential as you can
see here but they're consumed in
incredibly high quantities
i think sodium potassium etc another
thing you'll notice here in the minerals
box that i haven't talked about is the
red outline
that means there's a toxicity limit that
is known and somewhat realistic again as
i said everything on this board can be
toxic if you go crazy
but these are the things where people
can get sometimes through food though
that is rare but very very commonly
through basic supplementation
the second major category of minerals
are what are called trace or ultratrace
and this typically means you're
consuming less than 100 milligrams
daily or so and here is your list there
now notice they are also essential
but you need much smaller amounts of
them the vitamins are split up into two
major categories fat soluble
and water soluble vitamin a e k and d
now d is separate because it is
conditional that's the only one that you
can get through say the sun you don't
necessarily have to eat it
and a is also outlined there because it
is the most likely one you'll have
toxicity issues with the water soluble
ones like i said also essential
and you can see them there so there you
have it folks all of your macro
micronutrients explain it under five
minutes as promised
now if you enjoyed this you better
believe there's a lot more like this
coming
very very soon stay tuned